Guide to the Norbert George Barr Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Norbert George Barr Papers
1942-1953.
Barr, Norbert George, 1901-
12.5 linear ft (ca. 23,000 items in 30 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
MS#0081
4078961
This collection contains documents, manuscripts, printed material and photographs relating to Barr's service with U.S. Army Military Intelligence and the U.S. Displaced Persons Commission, in addition to personal correspondence.
Biographical Note
Writer, journalist. Born in Vienna, Austria, Barr was a free-lance news photographer and journalist from 1925 to 1939, traveling extensively in Europe and the Middle East. He enlisted in the U.S. Army in 1942 and was discharged in 1945.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, photographs, and printed materials. The papers cover the years 1942-1953, during which time he served with the U.S. Army Military Intelligence, participated in the Nürnberg war crimes trials, and was employed by the U.S. Displaced Persons Commission. At Nürnberg, he first held the position of interrogator and later helped edit trial documents for publication. The correspondence is largely of a personal nature, although some is work-related. With the manuscripts are three bound typescript carbon copies of essays on Nazi Germany by Herbert Pohle von Dziecielski, an engineer in the Speer ministry. The majority of the collection consists of interrogation summaries of presoners of war and defendants. Among other materials, there are also numbered 3x5 cards listing items of evidence, documents and evidence on individuals and institutions, a translation of the journal of the German Chief of the Army General Staff from August 14, 1939 to September 24, 1942, and reports on displaced persons. The photographs are few: most are of an unidentified possible atrocity. The printed materials, in English, French, German, include newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and books and range in date from 1937 to 1951.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in one series:
Series I: Norbert George Barr Papers, 1942-1953
Subjects
Germany.--Oberkommando der Wehrmacht.; United States.--Displaced Persons Commission.; United States.--Dept. of the Army.--General Staff.--Military Intelligence Division.; Von Dziecielski, Herbert Pohle.; Germany--History--1933-1945.; Germany--History--1945-1990.; Nuremberg Trial of Major German War Criminals, Nuremberg, Germany, 1945-1946.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945--Atrocities.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; Refugees--Europe.; Political refugees--Europe.; War crime trials--Germany (West); National socialism.; Photoprints.; Journalists.; News photographers.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
03/02/1983 M83-03-02
Transferred from the Law Library, 1983.
- Series I: Norbert George Barr Papers, 1942-1953
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Subject File A-Es (Box 1)
    - Anhaltische Kohlenwerke (Box 1)
    - Anti-Semitic Propaganda (Box 1)
    - Breder, Reinhard (Box 1)
    - Business Law (Box 1)
    - Central Planning Board (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Prisoners Held at Nuernberg (Box 1)
    - Depositions - Moosburg (Box 1)
    - Depositions - Nuernberg (Box 1)
    - Deutsche Kohlenbergbau-Gesellschaft (Box 1)
    - Deutsche Waffenstillstand Delegation (Box 1)
    - Dietrich, Otto - Document Book IVB (Box 1)
    - Displaced Persons (Box 1)
    - Economic Leaders (Box 1)
    - Essener Steinkohlenbergwerke Aktiengesellschaft (Box 1)
  - Subject File Ex-L (Box 2)
    - Exhibit Index - Defense (Box 2)
    - Exhibit Index - Prosecution (Box 2)
    - Flick, Friedrich (Box 2)
    - H.A. Brassert & Co., Inc. (Box 2)
    - Hanneken, Hermann von (Box 2)
    - Himmler, Heinrich (Box 2)
    - Hitler Assassination Attempt - July 20,1944 (Box 2)
    - Huegel, Klaus (Box 2)
    - Investigative Reports (Box 2)
    - Kehrl, Hans (Box 2)
    - Kriminalbiologische Untersuchungsatten... in Köln über Schaps, Karl Israel (Box 2)
    - Krupp Firm (Box 2)
    - Liberated Areas - Halle (Box 2)
    - Liberated Areas - Leipzig (Box 2)
    - Liberated Areas - Notes on Suspects (Box 2)
    - Liberated Areas - Stolberg (Box 2)
    - Lindemann, Karl (Box 2)
  - Subject File M-Po (Box 3)
    - Memoranda - 1946 (Box 3)
    - Memoranda - 1947 (Box 3)
    - Memoranda - 1948 (Box 3)
    - Memoranda - 1949-1950 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous - General (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous - Legal Papers (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous - Military Papers (Box 3)
    - Musy, Jean-Marie (Box 3)
    - Personal Papers (Box 3)
    - Personal Papers - Military (Box 3)
    - Personnel - Subsequent Proceedings Division (Box 3)
    - Pleiger, Paul (Box 3)
    - Pohl, Oswald (Box 3)
    - Pohle von Dziecielski, Herbert (2) (Box 3)
  - Subject File Pu-Sa (Box 4)
    - Publications Division (3) (Box 4)
    - Reichsfinanzministerium (Box 4)
    - Robert Bosch G.M.B.H. (Box 4)
    - Rogowski, Ernst (Box 4)
    - SS (Box 4)
    - Sauckel, Fritz (Box 4)
    - Saupert, Hans (Box 4)
    - Saur, Karl Otto (Box 4)
  - Subject File Sch (Box 5)
    - Schaeffer, Ernst (Box 5)
    - Schellenberg, Walter (3) (Box 5)
    - Schellenberg, Walter - Defense Documents (Box 5)
    - Schellenberg, Walter - Prosecution Briefs (Box 5)
    - Schroeder, Kurt Freiherr von (Box 5)
  - Subject File Sk-T (Box 6)
    - Skorzeny, Otto W. (Box 6)
    - Slave Labor - French Witnesses (2) (Box 6)
    - Speer, Albert (Box 6)
    - Thyssen, Fritz (Box 6)
    - Transcripts (Box 6)
    - Translated Documents (Box 6)
  - Subject File W (Box 7)
    - Waneck, Wilhelm (Box 7)
    - Wiegand, Ferdinand (Box 7)
    - Wirtschaftspolitik (Box 7)
    - Witness List - A-L (Box 7)
    - Witness List - M-Z (Box 7)
    - Wolf, Karl (Box 7)
  - Photographs (Box 7)
  - Manuscripts (Box 8)
    - "America Today" script - June 6, 1945 (mimeograph) (Box 8)
    - Goldschmidt, Jakob - Dr. Hjalmar Horace Greeley Schacht (typescript) (Box 8)
    - Krohn, Johannes - Die Sozialpolitik im Deutschen Wiederaufbrau (carbon copy) (Box 8)
    - Personal Writings (carbon copies) (Box 8)
    - Pohle von Dziecielski, Herbert - Covering Letters for MSS (Box 8)
    - Pohle von Dziecielski, Herbert - Leid und Tränen (bound carbon copy) (published?) (Box 8)
    - Pohle von Dziecielski, Herbert - Ruckshau ins Gestrige (bound carbon copy) (published?) (Box 8)
    - Pohle von Dziecielski, Herbert - Was Hitler Zerschlug (bound carbon copy) (published?) (Box 8)
    - Pohle von Dziecielski, Herbert - Was Hitler Zerschlug (carbon copy) (Box 8)
    - Pohle von Dziecielski, Herbert - Woran Deutschland Zerbach (bound carbon copy) (published?) (Box 8)
    - Publications Division - Drafts (Box 8)
  - Interrogation Summaries
    - A-Bo (Box 9)
    - Br-D (Box 10)
    - E-F (Box 11)
    - G-Han (Box 12)
    - Har-Hu (Box 13)
    - I-Kl (Box 14)
    - Kn-Lh (Box 15)
    - Li-Mr (Box 16)
    - Mu-P (Box 17)
    - Q-R (Box 18)
    - S-Schr (Box 19)
    - Schu-Sz (Box 20)
    - T-Wei (Box 21)
    - Wel-Z (Box 22)
    - Index A-Z (Names typed in red in index are found in this collection) (Box 22)
  - Displaced Persons Reports (Box 23)
  - Journal of the German Chief of the General Staff (Box 24)
    - Vol. 1 "The Polish Campaign. Part 1" August 14, 1939-September 10, 1939 (Box 24)
    - Vol. 2 "The Polish Campaign. Part 2" September 11, 1939-December 6, 1939 (Box 24)
    - Vol. 3 "Winter 1939/1940" December 7, 1939-May 9, 1940 (Box 24)
    - Vol. 4 "The Campaign in France" May 10, 1940-0ct. 30, 1940 (Box 24)
    - Vol. 5 (untitled) October 31, 1940-February 20, 1941 (Box 25)
    - Vol. 6 "The Campaign in Russia. Part 1" February 21, 1941-July 31, 1941 (Box 25)
    - Vol. 7 "The Campaign in Russia. Part 2" August 1, 1941-September 24, 1942 (Box 25)
  - Card Files - Evidence (Box 26)
    - Box 1: Cards with "MI" numbers, 1924, 1926, 1931-1941 miscellaneous cards. (Box 26)
    - Box 2: "NI" 1941-1942 (Box 25)
    - Box 3: Cards with "NG" numbers (handwritten), 4800-5499 (incomplete) miscellaneous "NG" cards (Box 25)
    - Box 4: Cards with "NG" numbers (typescript), 005-799 (incomplete) (Box 27)
    - Box 5: 800-2998 (Box 27)
    - Box 6: 3002-3599 (Box 27)
    - Box 7: 3600-4299 (Box 28)
    - Box 8: 4300-5199 (Box 28)
    - Box 9: 5200-5828 desk calendars for 1947 and 1948 with appointments (Box 28)
  - Card Files - Prisoners (Box 29)
    - "Germans Expected" A-Z, "Germans Here" A-Z, "Germans Released" A-Z (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous cards (Box 29)
  - Printed Material (Box 30)